A Guide to the Bernard J. Henley Papers, 1917-1989
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Bernard J. Henley Papers, 1917-1989
Library of Virginia
33623
13.25 cu. ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Bernard J. Henley Estate, 10 September 1989.
Biographical/Historical Information
Bernard J. Henley was born on 7 November 1909. He was a resident of Richmond, Virginia, and was employed as a librarian with the Richmond Public Library for 37 years, retiring on 20 May 1967. He died on 18 February 1989.
Scope and Content Information
Papers, 1917-1990, consisting of newspapers abstracts, genalogical notes, subject files, card files, and clippings. The NEWSPAPER ABSTRACTS include: a) Marriages and Deaths, arranged by newspaper locality, and thereunder chronologically. Newpapers covered include those from Alexandria, Fredericksburg, Norfolk, Petersburg, Richmond, as well as other cities in Virginia and West Virginia; b) Richmond - People, arranged alphabetically by surname; c) Richmond - Topical, 1737-1960, arranged chronologically, including Common Hall/Council Records Abstracts, 1789-1853; d) Topical - By Subject, including questions and answers about Richmond subjects, as well as information on general subjects and Confederate topics.
The GENEALOGICAL NOTES include information on the Blalock, Dowdy, Henley, and Orange families. This series includes abstracts and transcriptions from Bible records, census records, court records, land and personal property tax records, marriage records, vital statistics records, as well as extracts from published sources, newspaper clippings, and obituaries.
The SUBJECT FILES contain information on a variety of topics, especially relating to Richmond history, and Henley's involvement in the Virginia Place Name Society.
The CARD FILES include marriages and obituaries, subjects, poetry (by title or first line), subjects - chronological, Richmond City Council ordinances and resolutions, Acts of Assembly, information on the Henley and Dowdy families, addresses, call slips, and miscellaneous cards. There is a second series of card files that were found at a later date and have not been scanned, so consequently do not appear on the Library's Digital Collections page. This second group contains some of the same topics as the first, but others as well. For a detailed list, see the collection inventory.
There are also printed illustrations, published material, including pamphlets, brochures, and booklets, as well as photographic negatives and miscellaneous newspaper clippings.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: I. NEWSPAPER ABSTRACTS (Marriages and Deaths, Richmond-People, Richmond-Topical (Chronological), Topical (By Subject). II. GENEALOGICAL NOTES. III. SUBJECT FILES. IV. PRINTED ILLUSTRATIONS. V. PUBLISHED MATERIAL. VI. CARD FILES (Card Files - Series Two). VII. PHOTOGRAPHIC NEGATIVES. VIII. CLIPPINGS.
Contents List
- Newspaper Abstracts
  - Marriages and Deaths
    - Early Virginia Newspapers, 1736-1799 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Alexandria, 1800-1820 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Fredericksburg and Richmond, 1789-1799, 1838-1839, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Virginia Cities (F, H, L), 1800-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5-6, 6a)
    - Norfolk, 1796-1830 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Norfolk and Portsmouth, 1800-1839 (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
    - Petersburg, 1800-1859 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Richmond, 1800-1845 (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
    - Richmond, 1808-1830 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Richmond, 1828-1859 (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
    - Virginia Cities (S, W), 1800-1851 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Virginia (Now West Virginia) Cities, 1810-1840 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Richmond - People
    - A-M (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - N-Z (Box 3, Folder 4-7)
  - Richmond - Topical (Chronological)
    - 1737-1795 (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
    - 1795-1807 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - 1808-1817 (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
    - 1818-1829 (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
    - 1830-1840 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - 1840-1849 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
    - 1850-1862 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
    - 1863-1866 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
    - 1867-1872 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - 1873-1879 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
    - 1880-1887 (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
    - 1888-1892 (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
    - 1893-1900 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - 1901-1904 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
    - 1905-1907 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1903-1914 (Notebooks) (Box 7, Folder 6-7)
    - 1914-1933 (Notebooks) (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
    - 1933-1960 (Notebooks) (Box 8, Folder 4-6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8, Folder 7-9)
    - 1877-1941 (Rough Notes) (Box 9, Folder 1-42)
    - Common Hall/Council Records Abstracts, 1789-1853 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Richmond - Topical (By Subject)
    - Richmond (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
    - Richmond, Questions/Answers (Box 10, Folder 5-7)
    - General (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Mostly Confederate (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Richmond (A-S) (Box 11, Folder 1-18)
    - Richmond (T-Z) (Box 12, Folder 1-4)
    - Virginia (A-M) (Box 12, Folder 5-17)
    - Virginia (N-W) (Box 13, Folder 1-10)
    - Misc. Abstracts (Box 13, Folder 11-12)
    - Misc. Court Records Abstracts (Box 13, Folder 13-14)
    - Misc. Newspaper Abstracts (Box 13, Folder 15-18)
- Genealogical Notes
  - Blalock and Misc. (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Dowdy (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
  - Henley (Box 14, Folder 4-6)
  - Henley, A-H (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Henley, I-M (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Henley, N-Z (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Henley (Goochland) (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Henley (By County) (Box 15, Folder 1-3)
  - Orange (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Subject Files
  - AARP (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Anecdotes (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Bookplates (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Booth (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Calvary Baptist Church (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Certificates and Diplomas (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Civil War Stories (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Contributions (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Discharge Papers (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Financial Records (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Goochland (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Henley, Hezekiah (Box 15, Folder 18)
  - Henley, Richardson (Box 15, Folder 19)
  - Henrico (Box 15, Folder 20)
  - Jews (Abstracts, 1958-1960 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Land Records (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Maryland Gazette (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Microfilm Listing (Library of Virginia) (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 16, Folder 5-10)
  - Moon, W.A. (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Morton, Julia B. (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Negro Members of the General Assembly (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Oakley (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Pendleton (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Photographs (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Richmond Chronology (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Richmond Landmarks (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Richmond Public Library (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Richmond Suburban Development (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Richmond Times Articles, 1888-1895 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Selective Service (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Valentine Museum (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Place Name Society Newsletters, 1972-1979 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Place Name Society Occasional Papers (Box 17, Folder 10-12)
  - Virginia Place Name Society Publications (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Words (Box 17, Folder 14)
- Printed Illustrations
  - Fort Moultrie (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Fort Sumter (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Jamestown (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - La Salle (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Lee, Robert E. (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Lincoln, Abraham (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Madison, James (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Manassas, 2nd Battle of (Bull Run) (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Maryland (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - McKinley, William (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Middle Ages (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Missouri (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Monitor-Merrimac Battle (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - New Jersey (Box 18, Folder 14)
  - New York (Box 18, Folder 15)
  - Norseman in America (Box 18, Folder 16)
  - North Carolina (Box 18, Folder 17)
  - Ohio (Box 18, Folder 18)
  - Persia (Box 18, Folder 19)
  - Rhode Island (Box 18, Folder 20)
  - Rome, Ancient (Box 18, Folder 21)
  - Royalty, English (Box 18, Folder 22)
  - Seminole War (Box 18, Folder 23)
  - South Carolina (Box 18, Folder 24)
  - Spotsylvania Courthouse, Battle of (Box 18, Folder 25)
  - Stowe, Harriet Beecher (Box 18, Folder 26)
  - Texas (Box 18, Folder 27)
  - Utah (Box 18, Folder 28)
  - Washington, D.C. (Box 18, Folder 29)
  - Westward Movement (Box 18, Folder 30)
  - Williamsburg, Battle of (Box 18, Folder 31)
  - World War I (Box 18, Folder 32)
  - World War II - Europe (Box 18, Folder 33)
  - Yorktown (Box 18, Folder 34)
- Published Material
  - Miscellaneous Pamphlets, Brochures, Booklets, etc. (Box 19-21)
- Card Files
  - Marriages and Obituaries (Box 22-23)
  - Subjects (Box 24-27)
  - Poetry (By title or first line) (Box 28-30)
  - Chronological (Box 30)
  - Richmond City Council Ordinances and Resolutions (Box 30)
  - Acts of Assembly (Box 30)
  - Henley (Box 31)
  - Dowdy (Box 31)
  - Addresses (Box 31)
  - Call Slips (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 31)
  - Card Files - Series Two
    - Marriages (Box 32)
    - Ministers' Returns (Box 32)
    - Deaths (Box 32)
    - Subjects (Annexations, Churches, Civil War, Library Construction, Railroads, Schools, Colleges, Universities) (Box 33)
    - Poetry (Box 33)
    - Letters (Box 33)
    - Illustrations (Box 34)
    - Monuments (Box 34)
    - Richmond City Council Ordinances/Resolutions (Box 34)
    - Acts of Assembly (Divorces) (Box 34)
    - Proclamations (Box 34)
    - Henley Subjects (Box 34)
    - Dowdy Subjects (Box 34)
    - Richmond Info/Place Names (Box 34)
    - Virginia Info/Place Names (Box 34)
    - Land Sales (Box 35)
    - People (Box 35)
    - Newspaper Articles-Virginia/U.S. (Box 36)
    - Newspaper Articles-Richmond (Box 36)
    - Call Slips (Box 37)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 37)
    - Newspaper Titles (Box 37)
    - Family Names (Box 37)
    - Library Journal Proofs (Box 37)
- Photographic Negatives
  - (Box 38-38a)
- Clippings
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings (Box 39-43)